<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Evan Welsh</title>
  <link href="http://evanwelsh.com/atom.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="http://evanwelsh.com/" />
  <updated>2018-07-31T15:37:04+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://evanwelsh.com</id>
  <author>
    <name>Evan Welsh</name>
    <email>contact@evanwelsh.com</email>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>GUADEC Thoughts</title>
    <link href="http://evanwelsh.com/2018/07/16/guadec-thoughts/" />
    <updated>2018-07-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://evanwelsh.com/2018/07/16/guadec-thoughts</id>
    <content type="html">
      <h1 id="guadec-thoughts">GUADEC Thoughts</h1>
      <h2 id="background">Background</h2>
      <p>
        This month I had the amazing opportunity to attend GUADEC, the GNOME
        community conference in Europe! The GNOME Foundation generously
        sponsored this trip as part of my Google Summer of Code project and I
        can’t thank them enough!
      </p>
      <h2 id="location">Location</h2>
      <p>
        This year GUADEC took place in Almería, Spain at the Universidad de
        Almería. We couldn’t have asked for a better location. The city offered
        amazing cultural opportunities and the university space was
        well-maintained, had excellent WiFi, and a very kind staff!
      </p>
      <h2 id="day-0">Day 0</h2>
      <p>I arrived!</p>
      <h2 id="day-1">Day 1</h2>
      <p>
        I started off GUADEC right by volunteering at check-in. I made many
        buttons at the merchandise stand for eager attendees and diagnosed some
        interesting CUPS driver errors.
      </p>
      <p>
        From there, I moved on to practicing for my lightning talk with Carlos
        Soriano. All of the interns present gave a short presentation on their
        work, it served as a great time to bond with the other interns and sync
        into their work.
      </p>
      <p>
        After the lightning talks, the first day of GUADEC - gone in a second -
        came to a close and we moved to the beach for an exciting Beach Party!
        This was my first taste of the Mediterranean and it wouldn’t be my last.
      </p>
      <h2 id="day-2">Day 2</h2>
      <p>
        I started Day 2 with
        <a
          href="https://2018.guadec.org/pages/talks-and-events.html#abstract-30-javascript_in_gnome_in_2018"
          >JavaScript in GNOME in 2018</a
        >
        and thoroughly enjoyed the work Philip has put in over the course of
        this year. I stayed in the room to see
        <a
          href="https://2018.guadec.org/pages/talks-and-events.html#abstract-25-making_a_phone_call_with_gnome"
          >Making a Phone Call in GNOME</a
        >
        which was an interesting introduction to the upcoming Purism Phone and
        also a fascinating look into the telephony stack of GNOME. It certainly
        caught my eye and I will be following their development blog closely.
      </p>
      <p>
        I took a short break from talks at this point and got together with Avi,
        my fellow GNOME JavaScript intern, for some interesting discussions on
        GJS Linting and Developer Experience in the BoF/Hackspace.
      </p>
      <p>
        I returned to the talks to see some interesting work by Slimbook and
        then was exciting to attend my first GNOME Annual Meeting! It was great
        to see the board discuss the future of GNOME and how they plan to
        allocate the recent donations they’ve received!
      </p>
      <p>
        At the end of the day a few friends and I split off from the group,
        grabbed some food from a local market, and had a nice picnic in a local
        park. We joined the group again for the end of a fantastic castle tour
        and a beautiful dance show afterwards.
      </p>
      <h2 id="day-3">Day 3</h2>
      <p>
        Today marked the final day of official GUADEC! I very much enjoyed the
        final lightning talks which were an excellent opportunity for fun GNOME
        projects, interesting life skills (lock-picking :D), and amazing human
        beings to all come together.
      </p>
      <p>
        And with that the official conference was done and it was time to BoF!
      </p>
      <h2 id="day-4">Day 4</h2>
      <p>
        On the first day of BoFs I volunteered my first few hours helping
        organize t-shirts and cleanup the conference supplies with Kat. From
        there, I spent time with friends in the hackfest room working some GJS
        developer tools that we had discussed earlier in the conference.
      </p>
      <p>
        The day ended with a nice trip to the beach with my fellow interns and
        we build our first sandcastle. Little did we know this would be the
        prototype for
        <a
          href="https://wiki.gnome.org/GUADEC/2018/Hacking%20days/SandcastleBoF"
          >Sandcastle BoF</a
        >
        the following day.
      </p>
      <h2 id="day-5">Day 5</h2>
      <p>
        The second day of BoF(s) was by far my favorite. I sat in on the GUADEC
        and Theming BoFs and had a great time offering my input and suggestions
        in addition to hearing interesting viewpoints from around the community.
      </p>
      <p>
        In the GUADEC BoF we talked a lot about how to better streamline the
        conference in the future and fix technical and logistical issues going
        forward. I’m working on better management inside of GitLab (more to
        follow!) and exploring dedicated hardware for mobile payment systems!
      </p>
      <p>
        For theming there was a lot of discussion on how to balance the needs of
        themers, app developers, and the community overall. I think we settled
        on a good framework moving forward: a palette-style API for downstream
        distro branding, a more limited, yet specified stock icon pack, and an
        extended community icon specification for other purposes.
      </p>
      <p>
        At the end of the day, exhausted. Niclas and I got everyone together for
        an exciting and amazing Sandcastle BoF! It was an excellent afternoon of
        everyone in GNOME coming together for some super fun and super relaxing
        beach time.
      </p>
      <h2 id="day-6">Day 6</h2>
      <p>
        On the final day of BoFs I joined the Developer Center group to discuss
        GJS’ work on developer documentation and ways forward for GNOME as a
        community.
      </p>
      <p>We discussed…</p>
      <ul>
        <li>A hackfest in February to work on a product</li>
        <li>
          Standardizing introductory tutorials on one, newcomer-friendly
          language and offering alternative languages later
        </li>
        <li>Platforms to build on</li>
        <li>Multiple language support</li>
        <li>
          Addressing the messy state of Developer Center as it stands today
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>
        Overall, after this BoF I felt very optimistic for the future of the
        GNOME development experience.
      </p>
      <p>
        In the afternoon I worked on GJS with Avi and Philip, but spent a bit of
        time with the Meson BoF debugging an issue I had with Meson and Babel
        integration and discussed improving the default build settings for Meson
        to reduce confusion in instances where files retain their names during
        compilation (JavaScript compilation).
      </p>
      <p>
        After a long day, I joined my friends in exploring Almería (we found a
        wonderful bakery!) before preparing to leave and departing via Bus to
        Madrid where I hopped on a plane back to home.
      </p>
      <p>Thanks again to the GNOME Foundation!</p>
      <p>
        <img
          src="/images/sponsorship.png"
          alt="Sponsored by the GNOME Foundation"
        />
      </p>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Monday Markdown</title>
    <link href="http://evanwelsh.com/2018/06/04/monday-markdown-1/" />
    <updated>2018-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://evanwelsh.com/2018/06/04/monday-markdown-1</id>
    <content type="html">
      <h1 id="monday-markdown-1">Monday Markdown #1:</h1>
      <p>Rewriting the Development Experience for GNOME Javscript</p>
      <h3 id="greetings-world-">Greetings World 😊</h3>
      <p>A lot has happened over the past few weeks!</p>
      <p>
        I’ve spent the first portion of the coding period focused on improving
        the documentation browser for GNOME Javascript. In 2015/16 ptomato began
        porting GIR sources (the source of most GJS documentation) to
        [DevDocs.io], an open-source documentation browser, using g-ir-doc-tool
        in gobject-introspection. He did excellent work and produced a
        functioning product that now lives at [devdocs.baznga.org]. My goals
        were to take the current product and incorporate GNOME theming, fix
        issues with incorrect documentation, rebase the project on upstream, and
        reorient some of the project’s features to better serve an object
        oriented and GNOME model.
      </p>
      <p>
        The first task I began was rebasing the project on upstream. Our fork
        was approx. 500 commits behind upstream, commits which included critical
        back-end fixes and front-end compatibility work. The merge introduced
        several bugs that took a few days to iron out. One CoffeeScript file
        ended up with a subtle arrow function syntax error that changed
        execution and broke some documentation loading, the Ruby on Rails
        routing was broken, etc.
      </p>
      <p>After the project was rebased, I began the GNOME-ification process!</p>
      <p>
        I began to introduce a GNOME-inspired theme (both from gnome.org and the
        GNOME HIG), working off this mockup:
      </p>
      <p>
        <img
          src="images/devdocs-mockup.png"
          alt="Mockup of GNOME DevDocs Theme"
        />
      </p>
      <p>
        I first began removing some absolute positioning from upstream’s
        front-end. Absolute positioning was used for numerous core elements
        instead of using modern solutions such as
        <code class="highlighter-rouge">display: flex</code>. This hindered easy
        design iteration as any minute change was liked to break another
        element. The numerous changes which I intended to implement in the new
        theme also functioned better in a responsive, flex layout.
      </p>
      <p><img src="images/current.png" alt="First Iteration" /></p>
      <p>
        Here you can see several improvements. Primarily, dropdowns have been
        eliminated when unnecessary, the header had been redesigned in a GNOME
        fashion, search has become a drop-down, and “enabled” vs. “disabled” has
        become “favorited” vs. “all”. The primary goal of the former changes was
        to make the site feel “GNOME-y”, the latter change was to make all the
        documentation accessible. For our purposes it made more sense to make
        everything visible than to disable some documentations and then force
        users to enable them to search, view, and utilize them.
      </p>
      <p><img src="images/current-5-30.png" alt="Second Iteration" /></p>
      <p>
        Here you can see that index pages for sources are now sorted by type
        instead of a simple alphabetical listing.
      </p>
      <p><img src="images/current-5-31.png" alt="Third Iteration" /></p>
      <p>
        In the third iteration there are many subtle CSS fixes, search has been
        made permanent instead of a dropdown (some user testing indicated the
        dropdown was confusing/less helpful). Here you can also see that we’ve
        removed “duplicate” entries and removed the namespace prefixes. Both of
        these changes make the site more usable and object-oriented friendly.
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          Duplicate entries occured where the “type” was merely an index of the
          functions and classed for a specific strings. See below for an
          illustration.
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>
        <img src="images/devdocs-4.png" alt="Problem with duplicate entries" />
      </p>
      <p>
        Under the hood, at this point we made several more improvements. The
        repository utilized the stable branch (currently gnome-3-28) of
        gobject-introspection along with patches to properly format
        documentation for DevDocs. In gobject-introspection I also fixed
        long-standing bugs that made methods that were not introspectable and
        thus not in GJS show in class documentation. The docker instance was
        also upgraded and version-fixed so it would not break do to dependency
        errors in the future.
      </p>
      <p>I think that’s it for this Monday Markdown, I’ll see you next week.</p>
      <p>Evan // rockon999 // ewlsh</p>
      <p>find me on matrix under rockon999.</p>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
